Guide to the Frederick Mortimer Clapp Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Subject Files, 1928-1963; Series II; 8.55; (21 boxes)
  - "U" General, 1932-1950; 7 (Box 63)
  - "V" General, 1932-1950; 8 (Box 63)
  - Vacation, 1943-1950; 2 (Box 63)
  - "W" General, 1932-1950; 10 (Box 63)
  - Walker, Emery, 1929 (Box 63)
  - Walters Art Gallery, 1946-1947 (Box 63)
  - Webb, Vanderbilt, 1947-1950; 2 (Box 63)
  - Weber, John, University of Pittsburgh, 1932-1935; 3 (Box 63)
  - Who's Who and Like Record, 1931-1950; 10 (Box 64)
  - "X-Y-Z" General, 1932-1950; 8 (Box 64)
  - Yale University Alumni, 1936-1950; 8 (Box 64)
- Writing and Research Files, 1917-1967; Series III; 11.09; (27 boxes)
  Arranged into three suberies: Titled Works, Poetry, and Lecture and Research Notes. Titled Works are arranged in alphabetical order by title. Poetry and Lecture and Research Notes are not arranged in any particular order.
  - Titled Works
    - Against a Background on Fire, notebooks and typescript and holograph drafts, 1938-1941; 6 (Box 65)
    - Arhats in Art, typescript drafts, 1925; 2 (Box 65)
    - "Assiduously Silence," typescript and holograph drafts, circa 1958-1961 (Box 65)
    - "Business Book," typescript and holograph draft of additions and changes, undated (Box 66)
    - Cadenza in C Minor, typescript and holograph drafts, circa 1956-1960; 6 (Box 66)
    - Cadenza in C Minor, typescript and holograph drafts and proofs, circa 1956-1960; 10 (Box 67)
    - "Death Valley," typescript draft, undated (Box 68)
    - "50 Recent Poems," typescript draft, undated (Box 68)
    - The Frick Collection: Paintings: Summary Catalogue, correspondence and proofs, circa 1928-1930; 4 (Box 68)
    - "How to Make the Frick More Open to Public," holograph and typescript notes and research, undated (Box 69)
    - A History of the 17th Aero Squadron, typescript draft and proofs, 1918; 2 (Box 69)
    - Joshua Trees, holograph and typescript drafts, 1922; 2 (Box 69)
    - "The Lamellated Shell," typescript draft, undated; 4 (Box 70)
    - "Latest Poems," typescript draft and carbon copies, 1966; 3 (Box 70)
    - "Latest Poems," typescript drafts, 1966; 2 (Box 71)
    - "Latter Verses (1928-1929)," typescript draft, circa 1928-1929 (Box 71)
    - New Poems, holograph and typescript drafts, 1936; 3 (Box 71)
    - New Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and galley proofs, 1936; 5 (Box 72)
    - New York and Other Verses, typescript and holograph drafts and printed book, 1918; 3 (Box 72)
    - On the Overland, and Other Poems, typescript and holograph draft, undated (Box 73)
    - "Remarks on Poems for Poetry Reading," holograph and typescript notes and printed materials, undated (Box 73)
    - Said Before Sunset, typescript and holograph drafts, proof copy, and reviews and newspaper clippings, circa 1938; 5 (Box 73)
    - The Seeming Real, typescript drafts with corrections, setting typescript, and proofs, 1947; 4 (Box 73)
    - "Translations from Modern French and Italian Poetry," typescript drafts with holograph notes and corrections, undated; 5 (Box 74)
    - "War Diary," holograph notebooks and typescript draft, 1918; 3 (Box 74)
  - Poetry, circa 1917-1967
    - Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and fragments, circa 1917-1967; 5 (Box 75)
    - Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and fragments, circa 1917-1967; 8 (Box 76)
    - Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and fragments, circa 1917-1967; 13 (Box 77)
    - Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and fragments, circa 1917-1967; 11 (Box 78)
    - Poems, holograph and typescript drafts and fragments, circa 1917-1967; 15 (Box 79)
  - Lecture and Research Notes
    - Lecture Notes
      - Lists of lectures (Box 80)
      - Aeschelus (Box 80)
      - Artists In Revolutionary Italy (Box 80)
      - Boston, 1924; 2 (Box 80)
      - Euripides (Box 80)
      - Freer, undated; 2 (Box 80)
      - Herodotus (Box 81)
      - Homer (Box 81)
      - Pindar, 2 (Box 81)
      - Plato (Box 81)
      - Plutarch (Box 81)
      - Sophocles, 2 (Box 81)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 3 (Box 81)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 6 (Box 82)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 6 (Box 83)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 6 (Box 84)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 7 (Box 85)
      - Miscellaneous lecture notes, 8 (Box 86)
    - Research and other notes
      - Autobiographical notes, 2 (Box 87)
      - Buddhist doctrine notes (Box 87)
      - Florentine art notes (Box 87)
      - How to turn the Frick house into a museum, 1931 (Box 87)
      - Intonation and accent in reading Italian poems (Box 87)
      - Neurological notes (Box 87)
      - "Next to last draft" (Box 87)
      - Lecture at Southwest Harbor, 1946 (Box 87)
      - Pontormo research and notes, 4 (Box 87)
      - Pontormo research and notes, 3 (Box 88)
      - Prophesies of Nostradamus and others (Box 88)
      - Vedic philosophy (Box 88)
      - Wend's lecture (Box 88)
      - Miscellaneous research notes, 12 (Box 88)
      - Notecards on Oriental Art (Box 89)
      - Notes and notebooks, 9 (Box 90)
      - Notes on new building for Dept. of Fine Arts, Pittsburgh, 1965 (Box 91)
      - Notes on Indian Philosophy (Box 91)
      - "My First Sanskrit Notebook" (Box 91)
      - Vedic Philosophy (Box 91)
      - Notes and notebook, 3 (Box 91)
- Personal Papers and Other Material, 1894-1967; Series IV; 12; (32 boxes)
  Arranged into eight subseries: Miscellaneous Letters; Calendars; Diaries and Address Books; War Documents; Financial and Legal Papers; Other Papers; Printed Material; and Photographs.
  - Miscellaneous Letters
    - Letters to F. M. and Maud Clapp, 1914-1916; 3 (Box 92)
    - Letters to Maud Clapp from Susan, 1916 (Box 92)
    - Letters to Maud Clapp from "H" (Box 92)
    - Letters to Maud Clapp from F. M. Clapp, 1914-1916; 5 (Box 92)
    - Letters to F. M. Clapp from Maud Clapp, 1915-1916; 2 (Box 93)
    - Postcards, circa 1912-1967 (Box 93)
    - Letter Book, "Carbon copies of some of my letters written while on vacation in 1936 and 1937, F. M. Clapp", 1936-1937 (Box 93)
    - Letter to William Maxwell from F. M. Clapp, 1946 (Box 93)
    - Draft of letter to F. M. Clapp from Robinson Jeffers, undated (Box 93)
    - Greeting card from Wanda Landowska, 1946 (Box 93)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 2 (Box 93)
  - Calendars
    - 1933, 1935-1937 1933, 1935-1937, 6 (Box 94)
    - 1939-1941 1939-1941, 3 (Box 95)
    - 1942-1944 1942-1944, 3 (Box 96)
    - 1945, 1947-1948 1945, 1947-1948, 3 (Box 97)
    - 1949-1951 1949-1951, 3 (Box 98)
    - 1952-1955 1952-1955, 3 (Box 99)
    - 1956-1961 1956-1961, 3 (Box 100)
    - 1962-1965, 1967 1962-1965, 1967, 3 (Box 101)
  - Diaries and Address Books
    - Journals, 1915-1916; 3 (Box 102)
    - British Isles vacation diary, 1928; 2 (Box 102)
    - Diary, 1929 (Box 102)
    - The Ghost of My Friends, signature book, 1906-1907 (Box 102)
    - Address books, 4 (Box 103)
  - War Documents
    - Military service and discharge correspondence, 1917-1919; 2 (Box 104)
    - Portfolio for Important Documents, 1915-1918; 4 (Box 104)
    - Royal Flying Corps, Canada--Orders, 1917 (Box 105)
    - Royal Flying Corps, Canada--Notes on Aeriel Tactics, circa 1917 (Box 105)
  - Financial and Legal Papers
    - Account books, 1915, 1919-1921; 2 (Box 106)
    - Check stubs, 1913-1915, 1919; 2 (Box 106)
    - Bank account book, Livret National, 1914 (Box 106)
    - Stock certificate, 1922 (Box 106)
    - Real estate documents, 1926-1938 (Box 106)
    - Tax receipt, Yankee Point, 1932-1939 (Box 106)
    - Tax returns (missing several years), 1952-1967; 9 (Box 106)
    - Summary of Investments, 1953-1961; 2 (Box 107)
    - Income Tax - Correspondence and Data (Box 107)
    - Last Will and Testament, Maud Clapp (copy) (Box 107)
    - Copy of the Codicil to the Last Will of Maud Caroline Clapp, 1950 (Box 107)
    - Tax, 1951 (Box 107)
    - Will - F. M.C. (Codicil), Receipt (Box 107)
    - Estate of Maud C. Clapp, correspondence (Box 107)
    - Maud C. Clapp, biography data (Box 107)
    - Mr. West's letter of May 1/61 enclosing Federal Tax on M's Estate, 1961 (Box 107)
    - Income and Expenses, 1960-1961 (Box 107)
    - Robertson's letter of June 23/60 to W. Wescott re: Estate M.C.C., 1960 (Box 107)
    - Income Account - Maud Clapp, Bank Statements (N.Y. Trust), 1958 (Box 107)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 4 (Box 107)
  - Other Material
    - Passports and other documents, 3 (Box 108)
    - French identification papers, 2 (Box 108)
    - Souvenir Log, S.S. President Adams (Box 108)
    - Souvenir Passenger List, T.K.K. S.S. Taiyo Naru, 1921 (Box 108)
    - Libretto di Famiglia Clapp-Ede, 1908 (Box 108)
    - Etched copper plate (Box 108)
    - Leather booklet (Box 108)
    - Clapp genealogy notes (Box 108)
    - Greeting card (blank) (Box 108)
    - "The Life and Poetical Works of Frederick Mortimer Clapp" by Marvin Magalaner (English Honors thesis), typescript copy, 1942 (Box 108)
    - Townsend Harris Medal (Box 108)
    - Memorial given to Clapp upon his retirement from the Frick Collection, 1951 (Box 109)
    - Diploma of Honorary Membership in the Royal Academy of Santa Luca, 1918 (Box 109)
    - Two graphite portrait sketches of F. M. Clapp, by Mrs. F. M. Clapp, undated
    - Linoleum block cut for portrait of F. M. Clapp, possibly by Mrs. F. M. Clapp, undated (Box 110)
    - Drawing by Denman Ross, 1922 (Box 110)
    - Mirage - San Francisco, imprints, 1907 (Box 110)
    - Drawing - plans for apartment, undated (Box 110)
    - Drawings (unattributed), undated (Box 110)
    - Writings of Others (Box 110)
      - Crutchley, Fanny. Diary, circa 1955-1958 (Box 110)
      - Garnett, Porter. "The Notification of Genia", 1928 (Box 110)
      - Greenhood, David. Poems, undated (Box 110)
      - Lowell, Amy. "On Christmas Eve" typescript poem, undated (Box 110)
      - Rice, John. Diary and poems, 1910, undated (Box 110)
      - T., M. K. "Pensées de Riquet", undated (Box 110)
      - Unattributed writings, undated (Box 110)
    - Sound recording (Box 110)
    - Academie Colarossi medallion, by J. LaGrange, in original leather case, 1894 (Box 133)
  - Printed Material
    Includes University of Pittsburgh bulletins, Frick Collection announcements, and various clippings and publications.
    - Printed material, 9 (Box 111)
    - Printed material, 7 (Box 112)
    - Printed material, 5 (Box 113)
    - Printed material, 2 (Box 130)
  - Photographs
    - Frederick Mortimer Clapp as a child (Box 114)
    - Portraits of Frederick Mortimer Clapp, 8 (Box 114)
      Includes negatives and a photographic plate.
    - Maud Clapp (Box 114)
    - Woman and child, undated (Box 129 (Oversize))
    - Print and Negative of Portrait of Frederick Mortimer Clapp by Maud Clapp, 2 (Box 114)
    - Frederick Mortimer Clapp and Carl Parker, 1906 (Box 114)
    - Maud, Chancellor and FMC at Carnegie Pitt football game, 1930 (Box 114)
    - "Photos and material about 1st world war while I was with the British" (Box 115)
    - "Photographs from the hospital at the front where Maudie was vice directrice in first world war and other photos" (Box 115)
    - "Photos taken in Venice after 1st world war with some of Tim and Maud and of Constance Fletcher and H.D." (Box 115)
    - "Various photos - some nice ones of us at Morristown" (Box 115)
    - Negatives of Arizona trip, 1921 (Box 115)
    - Casa Grande National Monument, Arizona - snapshots (Box 115)
    - Negatives and snapshots of various trips (Box 115)
    - Ede Family Photographs (Box 116)
    - Old Frick Art Reference Library Reading Room (Box 116)
    - "Photos I took in Florence of Dad..." (Box 116)
    - Photographs of Thomas Wilfred and photographs taken with The Clavilux (Box 116)
    - Exteriors and interiors, various (Box 116)
    - Snapshots (Box 116)
    - Unidentified portraits (Box 116)
    - Negatives of miniatures and drawings (Box 116)
    - Cabinet card photographs (Box 116)
    - Aerial photographs, 2 (Box 117)
    - "Unicorns - Negative Photostats of" (Box 117)
    - Negatives, bookplate and plaque (Box 117)
    - "Photos of Arhats, etc..." (Box 117)
    - Reproductions of artwork (Box 117)
    - Photographs of China and Japan, 2 (Box 117)
    - Black and white and color tinted prints of foreign locales and people (some rolled), 8 (Box 118)
    - Unsorted photographs, 10 (Box 119)
    - Glass negatives (Box 131)
    - Glass negatives (Box 132)
- Maud Ede Clapp Papers, 1852-1960; Series V; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  Arranged into five subseries: Diaries, Writings, Notes, Artwork, and Ede Family Papers.
  - Diaries
    - 1885-1888 1885-1888, 2 (Box 120)
    - 1918 1918 (Box 120)
    - circa 1921? circa 1921? (Box 120)
    - 1921-1922 1921-1922 (Box 120)
    - 1922 1922, 2 (Box 120)
      Includes diary fragment with Maud's notes of canteen life during the First World War.
    - 1929-1930 1929-1930, 2 (Box 121)
    - 1932 1932 (Box 121)
    - 1934-1935 1934-1935 (Box 121)
    - 1936-1940 1936-1940, 6 (Box 122)
    - 1941, 1943-1945 1941, 1943-1945, 4 (Box 123)
    - 1946-1947, 1949 1946-1947, 1949, 3 (Box 124)
  - Writings
    - "New Views for Old Rugs," typescript drafts, corrected and final (Box 124)
    - "Paris in 1918" typescript and holograph draft fragments, 2 (Box 124)
    - "A Green Tent in Flanders," correspondence and holograph draft, 2 (Box 124)
  - Notes
    - M. Ede Etching Record, 1902-1906 (Box 125)
    - Maud's Notes on the War, 1917-1918 (Box 125)
    - Notebooks, 4 (Box 125)
    - UC Berkeley Lecture Notes (Box 125)
  - Artwork
    - Sketchbook (Box 126)
    - "Rialto," etching (Box 126)
    - Drawings (Box 126)
    - Plates, 2 (Box 126)
  - Ede Family Papers
    - Ede, Edward Francis
      - Notebook of poetry, 1852 (Box 126)
      - Diaries, 1886-1887; 2 (Box 126)
      - Diaries, 1895 (Box 127)
      - Account books, 1902-1909; 2 (Box 127)
    - Inventory, 1906, 1909 (Box 127)
    - Priscilla Ede Estate, 1909-1915, 1954-1960; 2 (Box 127)
    - Ede, C. Montague
      - Addresses to China, 1921 (Box 127)
      - Obituary, Hong Kong Weekly Press, 1925 (Box 127)
- Oversize, 0.38; (2 boxes)
  - The Frick Collection: Paintings: Summary Catalogue, proofs (from Series III), circa 1930; 2 (Box 128)
  - The Frick Collection: Paintings: Summary Catalogue, proofs (from Series III), circa 1930 (Box 129 (Oversize))
  - Diploma of Honorary Membership in the Royal Academy of Santa Luca (from Series IV), 1918 (Box 129 (Oversize))